Hey, what's up guys? My name is a
channel welcome back to my C + + series.
So today we're going to be talking all
about static analysis in C + + something
that is going to help you improve your
code. I think one of the most common
questions that I get is how can I make
my code better? How can I write code
that produces fewer bugs? Now ideally we
would be just amazing programmers who
write flawless code with our brains
would just be able to compute everything
on the fly. We would know exactly what
we're writing. If there's some kind of
error we could just foresee all of this
stuff happening, but the reality is
that's hard. Even for an experienced
programmer who's been working for
decades and is very well aware of how
computers work,
there's still going to be stuff that you
miss. And that's where you can use a
tool called a static analyzer to
actually look at your source code and
try and find problems with it. Now I
think the best way to look at this is to
think of yourself writing a word
document. Maybe you're writing some kind
of paper or an essay or some kind of
report. If you're writing that in
English or whatever your native language
is, chances are you're pretty good at
that language. I mean I would probably
expect a native English speaker to be
better at English than they are at C + +
at least I hope so. And of course this
translates to whatever your native
language is. But the point is you're
probably very good at that language. You
probably understand how spelling and
grammar work and you're a lot more used
to writing in that language than you
probably are writing in a programming
language such as C + +. But even though
you're very familiar with the language
that you're writing that document in,
you still typically use the spelling and
grammar checking tools. Inside your word
processor whether that be Microsoft Word
or Google Docs or something like that,
spelling mistakes and grammar errors or
just phrases that don't seem to make
sense are underlined for you. And I
imagine that you probably wouldn't want
to write a serious document without
having those tools available to you. You
probably wouldn't trust yourself to get
all of the spelling 100% right and all
of the grammar 100% right. Why not have
this little tool that just sits there
and checks your work to make sure that
it's correct? Now, if we're so eager to
rely on a tool like that to check our
native language for errors, wouldn't it
make sense to also have something like
that for whatever programming language
we're using? I mean, considering that
you're probably more likely to make a
mistake in C++ instead of in English,
for example, especially if you're less
experienced in the language and
especially if that language tends to be
C++. Now, programming is a little bit
different, of course. If you
accidentally misspell a variable name in
one place after it's already been
declared and defined,
that's probably going to result in a
compiler error. You're just not going to
be able to compile your code into a
program because the compiler won't be
able to make sense of what you've
written. That's a little bit different
than if you're just writing a word
document. Now, grammar mistakes, on the
other hand, and I'm not talking about
the actual like lexical grammar of the
language of C++, I'm more or less
talking about, you know, the intended
usage of the code that we've written.
Those mistakes, a compiler is never
going to catch because the compiler
doesn't really know what you're trying
to do. And in fact, its job is not to
try and predict what you're trying to do
and try and find mistakes in that. It
just needs to make sure that your code
is able to be compiled into some kind of
binary format that might be executed,
might be used elsewhere. It's not going
to actually dive into your code and
analyze it and try and make sure that
what you've actually written physically
in the code is what your intention was.
And that is exactly where a static
analyzer comes in. A static analyzer
will actually look at your code and try
and detect various errors that you may
have unintentionally written. Kind of
like a code review, but instead of a
person doing it,
the tool is just going to do it for you.
I honestly think that pretty much
everyone would benefit from static
analysis. If you just took a static
analyzer and ran it through your code, I
am sure that it would point out a few
things that are
at best questionable and at worst just
may completely wreck your life if you
don't fix them immediately. And it's
also quite a big deal in the games
industry. For example, Unreal Engine
uses static analysis. John Carmack has
mentioned that one of the most important
things that he's done in recent years
has been to pursue static analysis. So,
my point is that it can be an absolutely
useful asset to you. And in fact, of
course, it never hurts to get an
additional set of eyes looking at your
code. Now, there are a lot of different
static analyzers out there, and I
encourage you guys to check all of them
out. we're going to be specifically
talking about PVS-Studio, who are also
nice enough to sponsor this video. I've
talked about PVS-Studio before. It's one
of my favorite static analyzers. You
guys can check out this video from a
while back where I actually used it on
Hazel a little bit. It's incredibly
straightforward, verbose, and just I
mean, it just works. It just finds a lot
of errors in your code. What I want to
do is dive into some C++ code and just
show you some very basic examples of how
to get started using it and some of the
stuff that it can actually detect.
PVS-Studio comes in a variety of
flavors, one of which is a fantastic
Visual Studio extension, and that's what
we'll be using today. It's also
worthwhile to mention that PVS-Studio
supports C, C++, C#, and Java. But
today, of course, we'll be using it with
C++ code. After installing PVS-Studio
under extensions and then PVS-Studio,
you'll see basically all of the options
that they offer. If you go to options,
there's also a ton of various settings
that you can actually modify. The most
common tools that I tend to use are the
check current file, which is just a
little quick check to see what might be
wrong with the current file, and also
check current project or even solution,
which will actually check all of your
code. Now, there are a ton of different
things that PVS-Studio will actually
detect. I'm not going to attempt to show
you guys like all of them or anything
like that. I'll just show you some of
the stuff that it detects that I think
is really, really useful and probably
quite common. So, suppose that I need to
write a nested for loop because I want
to fill some kind of maybe like a color
buffer full of like pixel color values.
I might have some kind of buffer that
I've created here. I might just make
this a pointer and allocate it on the
heap here. There's going to be a certain
width, maybe 800, and a height that I
set up here. I'll allocate width times
height here, not forgetting this equal
sign. And then I might choose to write
some kind of for loop which just
iterates through maybe the width and the
height, maybe nested inside each other
to try and fill the buffer with a
certain color value, maybe black. So,
what I'll do is I'll write the outer for
loop first. I'll say for uint32_t y = 0,
y is less than height, y++.
And then, of course, for the inner loop,
I'll just copy this and I'll write it
out like this. So, we'll change this to
x,
uh and x is less than width, etc. Okay,
and then we'll just do buffer x + y *
width = maybe like 0. So, we're just
clearing it to 0. And of course, we
could just use a memset for this, but
that's not the point. We're
demonstrating a nested for loop example.
So, what we've done here is we've
actually made a small little mistake,
something that is not very apparent,
especially because we copied and pasted
the code. Let's go ahead and go to
extensions, PVS-Studio, and check the
current file. So, PVS-Studio will open
over here. We'll see a little prompt
here for a second, and then we'll get
the errors showing up here. So, it seems
to say two things. First of all, the
condition x less than width of loop is
always true. So, we can double click on
it. It will actually highlight it for
us. Okay, that's interesting. And then,
we have another one which is a little
bit more descriptive for this particular
case. It says here that it is likely
that a wrong variable is being
incremented inside the for operator.
Consider reviewing y. So, if we double
click on this, we can look at this and
we can consider reviewing y. Oh, look,
we've accidentally written y here
because I copied and pasted this code
and I must have forgotten to change this
from y to x. This is honestly an issue
that happens more often than you think.
I've made this mistake countless times,
not necessarily with an asset for loop
like this, but copying and pasting code
is something that is this completely
common in the life of a programmer.
You're continually copying and pasting
code and accidentally forgetting to
maybe change all of the variables is an
issue. And little mistakes like these
can actually just fly by until maybe a
month later they'll explode somewhere.
You might even accidentally ship code
with this. It really is a big deal and
it's something that we miss all the
time. Now, in this case, PVS-Studio
actually gave us two different error
messages. So, the condition x less than
width of loop is always true. This is
pretty cool. It means that since we've
actually set x to zero and then we're
evaluating x less than width, but then
we're never incrementing x, it means
that we're never going to satisfy the
condition of this loop. X will always
remain at zero and thus we've created an
infinite loop. And PVS is actually able
to detect all of that. It basically
executes our code inside its little
engine and sees what the output will
likely be. And that's one of the most
powerful features of PVS. The fact that
it has this little internal engine that
it can actually use to evaluate our
code. It's really cool. So, with this in
mind, I can come in and I can just
change this x here and then I can
validate this code once more through
PVS-Studio. And now we can see that we
have no error messages. Cool. Let's look
at another example. A lot of the time
when we're dealing with strings,
particularly like raw strings, maybe we
have like a const char string here and
it just says hello. When we're dealing
with strings, something that programmers
tend to do quite often is completely
forget about the null termination
character. Meaning that this little
backslash zero is actually inside this
buffer. If you take a look at the length
of the string, it's going to give you a
value of five because it is five
characters long. However, the buffer
required to actually store this should
be six bytes. Why? Because we have the
five letters, but then we also need that
null termination character. If we don't
have that and then the next byte is just
some other memory, we have no way of
actually telling how big the string is.
Is the next byte going to be part of the
string or is it something else entirely?
However, it's very common to forget
about that. And PVS-Studio is really
good at detecting exactly this. I'll
show you guys an example. What I might
do is attempt to create another buffer
here. I'll say new char and then maybe
what I do is I'll just measure the
length of the string and I'll forget the
plus one. So, instead of making sure
that I've got the length of the string
plus one more byte for the null
termination character, I will forget
that. And then what I'll attempt to do
is use string copy to actually copy our
original string into that buffer. So,
I'll write buffer as the destination and
string as the source. Now, if I run this
through PVS-Studio by going to
extensions PVS-Studio check current
file, it's telling me here that a call
of the string copy function will lead to
overflow of the buffer buffer. So, if I
double click on this, you can see that
it doesn't like the way that I've used
this function because it's going to
overflow this actual buffer. I could
also try and use mem copy instead. If I
just do mem copy buffer source and then
maybe let's just do string length of
string. Let's try and check that out.
You can see that it actually gives us an
even more descriptive error saying that
the mem copy function doesn't copy the
whole string. Use string copy \slash}
string copy s function to preserve
terminal null. So, it's telling us here
that we're actually not copying the
entire string because that null
termination character at the end, we're
not actually preserving it. Again,
really important stuff that you could
just execute this code and everything
would run fine, but of course you are
missing that null termination character.
Actually, you haven't even allocated
enough room for it. And these are all
things that PVS-Studio can detect. The
last example that I'll show you has to
do with basically just optimization
because PVS can not just find errors in
our code, it can actually help us
optimize our code as well. What I want
to do is write a very simple function.
It's going to maybe return this kind of
entity struct that we have. So, suppose
I have a struct called entity. I'll then
write a function called load entity
which potentially is supposed to just
load the entity, but what I'll do is
I'll purposely just make it return null
pointer all the time. So, all this
function really does is returns null
pointer. It's just supposed to serve as
a very, very simple example of some of
the stuff that PVS-Studio can actually
detect. So, I'll go ahead and try and
maybe call that function here
as you might in some example code here.
And then a pretty common check here is
to check to see if entity is null or
not, and I can do that by just writing
if entity. Now, in this case, this check
is absolutely not needed. We know that
entity is always going to be null. We
might as well not even have a branch
because that's going to needlessly slow
down our code. We don't need to do that.
We know that it's always going to be
null. And this is something that
PVS-Studio can actually detect. If we go
extensions, PVS-Studio check current
file, then you can see that it actually
tells us that expression entity is
always false. This is always false, this
expression. Now, the benefit here is
twofold. If in fact it is supposed to be
always false, then you can just remove
this branch completely and you've saved
yourself a branch. And at the very
least, if the compiler does in fact get
rid of that, you've cleaned up your code
considerably. However, if it's not
supposed to be always false, this is
going to lead to you uncovering an
actual error in the code that you've
written. Because looking at this,
clearly this is not always supposed to
be false. Load entity is not supposed to
always return null. So, you can go back
and take a look at your implementation
and make sure that you've actually
written the correct code. And that, I
think, is super useful. Okay, so
hopefully that was a little bit of an
introduction to static analysis and
PVS-Studio. This is definitely a huge
topic. I might cover more of this in the
future. It's just one of those things
that in practice is going to help you a
lot more than if I just theorize about
it all the time. You need to actually
download PVS-Studio and give it a go.
Now, normally PVS-Studio have a 7-day
free trial available. However, they've
been nice enough to give you guys a
30-day free trial. All you have to do is
check out the link in the description
below and use the appropriate code. The
other great thing about PVS-Studio is
that they have a ton of really, really,
really useful articles on their website.
I'll link some of my favorites in the
description below as well, but just
check out their blog. I mean, they they
literally have so much content on there
that's a good read even if you don't
choose to use PVS Studio. Some of the
errors that their software has detected
and that they've done a write-up about
has just been really helpful in general
just detailing some really hard to find
and critical bugs that you probably
wouldn't have even thought of. So,
definitely give PVS Studio a try, run it
on some of your own software projects
and let me know in the comment section
below what errors it picks up. I really
am interested to see all of the
different stuff that it can actually
detect. I hope you guys enjoyed this
video and I will see you next time.
Goodbye.